<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | B.A.B. Lab</title>
    <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/projects/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/media/icon_huf1d3085986ef1a427864a02e550ff7cd_65514_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/projects/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/projects/labrador_coastal_current/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/projects/labrador_coastal_current/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;export-and-cycling-of-trace-elements-by-the-labrador-coastal-current-and-labrador-current-the-last-conduits-of-fresher-arctic-water-to-the-north-atlantic-ocean&#34; style=&#34;color: darkblue&#34;&gt;Export and cycling of trace elements by the Labrador Coastal Current and Labrador Current: the last conduits of fresher Arctic Water to the North Atlantic Ocean&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Arctic Water (AW) trace element (TE) geochemistry has been well characterized along its flow path from the Chukchi Sea through the Canadian Arctic Archipelago and Baffin Bay, there is still a knowledge gap regarding the cycling and fluxes of TEs advected by the Labrador Coastal Current and Labrador Current across Newfoundland and the Labrador shelf, the only major AW outflows which have not yet been sampled for TEs at high resolution, and therefore, no accurate budgets have been established to date. This study will provide an integrated perspective about the evolution of the TEs and nutrient signature of AW along its journey from the Bering Strait to the Labrador Sea, as well as will shed light on freshwater apportionment by means of various tracers (e.g., oxygen isotopes, nutrients, barium, gallium).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborators&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www2.whoi.edu/staff/nfoukal/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nicholas Foukal (Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, USA)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ocean.washington.edu/home/Laramie_Jensen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Laramie Jensen  (University of Washington)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/projects/amazon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/projects/amazon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;iron-and-manganese-oxide-nature-and-bound-organic-carbon-abundances-in-the-amazon-shelf-the-effect-of-reductive-dissolution-and-oxidative-processes-on-carbon-stability&#34; style=&#34;color: darkblue&#34;&gt;Iron and manganese oxide nature and bound-organic carbon abundances in the Amazon Shelf: the effect of reductive dissolution and oxidative processes on carbon stability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mineral protection (e.g., clays) of organic carbon (OC) has been widely recognized as a significant factor controlling its stabilization, and thus, OC degradation rate and burial efficiency. Recent studies have been focusing on the OC “protective” effect of iron, and to a lesser extent manganese, minerals on OC stability. In this project, we will be investigating how the complex redox chemistry of Fe and Mn oxides influence OC cycling in the Amazon River/Shelf system, the largest river basin on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborators&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;: This project is framed within the larger MUDBENCS Amazon Project lead by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usf.edu/marine-science/faculty/faculty-directory/geological-oceanography/brad-rosenheim.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Brad Rosenheim (University of South Florida, USA)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www2.whoi.edu/staff/vgaly/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Valier Galy (Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, USA)&lt;/a&gt;, with whom we will be closely collaborating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/projects/rlp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/projects/rlp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;carbon-cycling-along-river-ocean-endmembers-a-case-study-of-the-rio-de-la-plata-estuary-argentina&#34; style=&#34;color: darkblue&#34;&gt;Carbon cycling along river-ocean endmembers: A case study of the Rio de La Plata Estuary, Argentina&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Large river systems along with continental margins are a central component of the Earth’s carbon cycle; they spatially integrate multiple carbon reservoirs (terrestrial, atmospheric and marine environments) and temporally link shorter timescale biological processes (e.g. primary production, remineralization) with larger timescale geological processes. In this project, we are studying the source to sink characterization of OC in the Rio de La Plata Estuary, the second largest South American river. The findings will be integrated with the better-studied Amazon River, thus expanding the South American perspective of global carbon cycling from the two largest rivers on this continent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborators&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www2.whoi.edu/staff/vgaly/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Valier Galy (Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, USA)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ri.conicet.gov.ar/author/27698&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Eric Speranza (National university of La Plata, Argentina)&lt;/a&gt; and Juan Carlos Colombo (National university of La Plata, Argentina).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
