<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>EnvirHealth | B.A.B. Lab</title>
    <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/tag/envirhealth/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/tag/envirhealth/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>EnvirHealth</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/media/icon_huf1d3085986ef1a427864a02e550ff7cd_65514_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>EnvirHealth</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/tag/envirhealth/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Initial assessment of multi-compound antineoplastic drug surface contamination in Argentinean healthcare centers: Insights into occupational exposures in South America
</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/jopp_2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/jopp_2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;JOPP2023.png&#34; width=&#34;900&#34; height=&#34;900&#34; border=&#34;10&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Introduction: Antineoplastic drug contamination can result in severe health effects for healthcare workers exposed to them. Despite the worldwide growing concern regarding these drugs and sustained monitoring efforts in developed countries, there is almost no data about surface contamination levels in Argentina, in particular, and South America, in general. Methods: Antineoplastic drug contamination was measured in three Argentinean public hospitals (pharmacy and daycare center areas) by surface wiping and liquid chromatography coupled with tandem mass spectrometry. Results and Discussion: Eleven drugs were detected, in 51 of 58 sampled surfaces, in variable concentrations from 0.00064 to 7.3 ng cm−2, with cyclophosphamide, gemcitabine, and paclitaxel as the most prevalent drugs. This highly variable antineoplastic distribution reflects differences in facility layout, number of patients, antineoplastic drug use, etc., at each hospital. Values exceeding the 1 ng cm−2 threshold were detected in 13 surfaces of the two hospitals handling the largest amounts of antineoplastic drugs. The cyclophosphamide 75th percentile averaged 0.030 ng cm−2 comparable to the high values reported more than 10 years ago for developed countries, emphasizing the potential of reducing antineoplastic contamination by implementing routine monitoring and improved cleaning and handling procedures. Conclusion: This study is the first survey of multi-compound surface antineoplastic contamination in Argentinean (and South American) hospitals, providing a baseline against which future studies can be compared. Widespread antineoplastic contamination has been detected on numerous surfaces, with concentrations surpassing suggested threshold exposure levels (1 ng cm−1) for some surfaces in two of the sampled hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The application of novel field measurement and field evaluation protocols for assessing health care workers’ exposure risk to antineoplastic drugs</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/joeh_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/joeh_2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;JOEH2020.png&#34; width=&#34;900&#34; height=&#34;900&#34; border=&#34;10&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Contamination of multiple antineoplastic drugs (ADs) on work surfaces presents an exposure concern for health care workers. Surface wipe sampling is a recognized method to evaluate the degree of contamination present. Our research team has previously reported on wipe sampling and analytical methods to simultaneously detect 10 commonly used ADs from a single wipe. Our objectives here were: to field test a protocol consisting of the wipe sampling method and an accompanying wipe sample collection tool kit and confirm this protocol can be effectively used by health care workers to assess drug contamination levels in their facilities; and, to confirm the potential for simultaneous exposure to multiple antineoplastic drugs. Three facilities within one health authority in British Columbia, Canada participated in this field study. In collaboration with the site health and safety advisors, up to 25 surfaces within each facility were considered for sampling. Collected wipe samples were analyzed using HPLC-MS/MS to quantify the 10 analyte, resulting in 750 potential analyses. Following the sampling, each of the three facilities’ safety advisors provided feedback regarding the usability of the protocols. Among the 72 wipe samples actually collected (or 720 analyses conducted), detectable levels and simultaneous contamination of work surfaces of five of the 10 analytes were found at all three participating sites: 5-fluorouracil, cyclophosphamide, vincristine, paclitaxel, and methotrexate; (range &amp;lt; LoD to 33.0 ng/cm2) with 5-fluorouracil having the highest concentration in every instance. Drug contamination was found on a variety of different work surfaces in pharmacies and patient care areas among all three sites. Users of the sampling protocols were generally satisfied with the wipe sample collection toolkit with some minor suggestions for improvement. Our findings support the hypothesis that health care workers may be simultaneously at risk of exposure to several ADs. Our toolkit was found to be user-friendly and manageable by those who were not experienced in collecting wipe samples to monitor contamination of ADs on the work surfaces in their facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wipe Sampling Method and Evaluation of Environmental Variables for Assessing Surface Contamination of 10 Antineoplastic Drugs by Liquid Chromatography/Tandem Mass Spectrometry</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/aweh_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/aweh_2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;AWEH.png&#34; width=&#34;900&#34; height=&#34;900&#34; border=&#34;10&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: This paper describes a novel wipe sampling and high-performance liquid chromatography/tandem mass spectrometry (HPLC-MS/MS) method capable of simultaneously detecting 10 antineoplastic drugs (5-fluorouracil, oxaliplatin, methotrexate, vindesine, ifosfamide, cyclophosphamide, vincristine, vinblastine, docetaxel, and paclitaxel). The good overall recoveries and sensitivity values of this method along with the comparatively short run time (8 min) allows for its use in routine monitoring in health care facilities. The long-term behavior of the studied drugs on contaminated surfaces and the effect of surface roughness on drug recoveries were studied to gain insights about how these environmental variables influence the detection, cleaning, and occupational exposure of these drugs. Surfaces with higher roughness parameter (Ra) values (rougher) had the lowest recoveries while those with lower Ra (smoother) presented the highest recoveries. Long-term assessments evidence distinctive drug behaviors with oxaliplatin, vindesine, vincristine, and vinblastine being the less persistent drugs (~20% was recovered after 24 h) and docetaxel and paclitaxel the most persistent drugs with recoveries of 40% and 80% after 1 month. This information indicates the importance of collecting ancillary information about drug usage (throughput, timing, cleaning procedures, etc.) to interpret the results in the context of potential exposure. Finally, the method was successfully applied to evaluate trace surface contamination down to the single picogram per square centimeter in multiple work areas within three local health care centers on Vancouver Island, Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A surface wipe sampling and LC–MS/MS method for the simultaneous detection of six antineoplastic drugs commonly handled by healthcare workers</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/abc_2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/abc_2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;ABC.png&#34; width=&#34;900&#34; height=&#34;900&#34; border=&#34;10&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: An effective wipe sampling and LC–MS/MS method was developed to simultaneously analyze six commonly administered antineoplastic drugs in stainless steel surface. The analyzed drugs were methotrexate, paclitaxel, cyclophosphamide, 5-fluorouracil, vincristine, and oxaliplatin, a frequently prepared antineoplastic drug that has not been included among any of the published simultaneous detection methods. The established method was used to evaluate the recoveries of antineoplastic drugs on brand new and worn stainless steel surfaces by wiping the plates with a Whatman filter paper wetted with 0.5 mL of water/methanol (20:80) with 0.1%formic acid followedbyLC–MS/MS before desorbing the filter with a water/methanol (50:50) solution. A significant decrease in the recovery of all evaluated drugs was found when worn plates were used. Additionally, the inter-personnel variability on drug recoveries during wiping procedures was evaluated. Significantly higher recoveries were achieved by the personnel with more training and experience versus personnel without prior experience. Finally, a laboratory stability test was developed to assess the degradation of the antineoplastic drugs during replicated shipping conditions. With the exception of vincristine sulfate which exhibited a significant (p&amp;lt;0.05) degradation after 48 h, all evaluated drugs were stable during the first 24–48 h. However, after 144 h, an increase in the degradation of all evaluated drugs was observed, with oxaliplatin and 5- fluorouracil exhibiting the most degradation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
