<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Latest News | B.A.B. Lab</title>
    <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Latest News</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/media/icon_huf1d3085986ef1a427864a02e550ff7cd_65514_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Latest News</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome!</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/post/welcome_vg_acr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/post/welcome_vg_acr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;#x1f389;&amp;#x1f389; Welcome &lt;a href=&#34;https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/author/athira-chakkalaparambil-rajendran/&#34;&gt;Athira Chakkalaparambil Rajendran&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/author/victoria-grisson/&#34;&gt;Victoria Grisson&lt;/a&gt;, the newest members of the B.A.B. Lab! This Fall, they will be starting their respective Ph.D. and M.S. programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Athira will be working on the project &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/projects/amazon/&#34;&gt;Iron and manganese oxide nature and bound-OC abundances in the Amazon Shelf: the effect of reductive dissolution and oxidative processes on OC stability&lt;/a&gt; and Victoria will be working on the project &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/projects/labrador_coastal_current/&#34;&gt;Export and cycling of trace elements by the Labrador Coastal Current and Labrador Current: the last conduits of fresher Arctic Water to the North Atlantic Ocean&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Paper Out!</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/post/new_paper_ocy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/post/new_paper_ocy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;#x1f389;&amp;#x1f389; Our new paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://tos.org/oceanography/article/shelf-basin-connectivity-drives-dissolved-fe-and-mn-distributions-in-the-western-arctic-ocean-a-synoptic-view-into-polar-trace-metal-cycling&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;“Shelf-basin connectivity drives dissolved Fe and Mn distributions in the western Arctic Ocean: A synoptic view into polar trace metal cycling”&lt;/a&gt; has been published. This paper showcases the grand effort and success of GEOTRACES international program in pursuing an unprecedent study on trace element biogeochemistry in the Arctic Ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through a fruitful collaboration, Laramie Jensen and I undertook a non trivial challenge: provide an integrated perspective on trace element biogeochemistry in the Arctic Ocean! In this paper we discuss the most important processes shaping trace element distribution in this unique environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Paper Out!</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/post/new_paper_lo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/post/new_paper_lo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;#x1f389;&amp;#x1f389;Our new paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://aslopubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/lno.12407&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;“Control of particulate manganese (Mn) cycling in halocline Arctic Ocean waters by putative Mn‐oxidizing bacterial dynamics”&lt;/a&gt; has been published. This large-scale field study combines trace element analysis with microbial data to unravel the geochemistry of Mn in the Canadian Arctic Ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through a cross disciplinary collaboration, we present the first holistic study of the biogeochemical cycling of particulate manganese (pMn), an essential micronutrient and reactive element, in the Canadian Arctic Ocean (CAO). By integrating pMn data with microbial community compositional data, we investigate the role of putative Mn-oxidizing bacteria in driving authigenic Mn precipitation in the CAO, especially in subsurface halocline waters. Additionally, our findings reveal the importance of low light intensity (reducing photoinhibition) and elevated dissolved Mn concentrations as the main environmental factors explaining the relatively large abundance Mn oxidizing bacteria found in water masses where pMn peaked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Paper Out!</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/post/new_paper_biogeo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/post/new_paper_biogeo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;#x1f389;&amp;#x1f389;The new paper, lead by collaborator &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eoas.ubc.ca/~brogalla/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Birgit Rogalla&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1029/2022JG007072&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;“Continental and Glacial Runoff Fingerprints in the Canadian Arctic Archipelago, the Inuit Nunangat Ocean”&lt;/a&gt; has been published. This study aims to provide a linkage between the terrestrial and marine environments, assessing the influence of freshwater inputs on biogeochemical cycles in the Canadian Arctic Ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rising temperatures and an acceleration of the hydrological cycle due to climate change are increasing river discharge, causing permafrost thaw, glacial melt, and a shift to a groundwater‐dominated system in the Arctic. These changes are funnelled to coastal regions of the Arctic Ocean where the implications for the distributions of nutrients and biogeochemical constituents are unclear. In this study, we investigate the impact of terrestrial runoff on marine biogeochemistry in Inuit Nunangat (the Canadian Arctic Archipelago) — a key pathway for transport and modification of waters from the Arctic Ocean to the North Atlantic — using sensitivity experiments from 2002‐2020 with an ocean model of manganese (Mn).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Paper Out!</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/post/new_paper_jop/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/post/new_paper_jop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;#x1f389;&amp;#x1f389;The new paper, lead by collaborator Eric D Speranza, &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/10781552231188320&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;“Initial assessment of multi-compound antineoplastic drug surface contamination in Argentinean healthcare centers: Insights into occupational exposures in South America”&lt;/a&gt; has been published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the growing concern regarding the passive occupational exposure to chemotherapy drugs, data from developing countries is extremely scarce, hindering the assessment of antineoplastic contamination in these countries where such drugs are increasingly used. As a first step towards filling this knowledge gap, we have measured antineoplastic drugs surface concentrations in multiple areas (i.e. Pharmacy, compounding room, daycare center patient hall) and surfaces of three representative public hospitals in Buenos Aires, Argentina, using well stablished wipe sampling and UPLC-MS/MS analysis. In this first survey in Argentina, we found complex and highly variable antineoplastic drugs distributions, accounting both for intra and inter hospital differences. Concentrations exceeding 1 ng cm-2 threshold level were found in several surfaces, pointing out the need for corrective actions to prevent occupational exposure of healthcare workers and public in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
