<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rivers | B.A.B. Lab</title>
    <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/tag/rivers/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/tag/rivers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Rivers</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/media/icon_huf1d3085986ef1a427864a02e550ff7cd_65514_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Rivers</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/tag/rivers/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Controlling factors and impacts of river-borne neodymium isotope signatures and rare earth element concentrations supplied to the Canadian Arctic Archipelago
</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/epsl_2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/epsl_2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;EPSL2022.png&#34; width=&#34;900px&#34; max-height= auto border=&#34;10&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Determining the factors controlling the neodymium (Nd) isotopic compositions (expressed as εNd) and rare earth element (REE) concentrations of rivers is imperative to improve our understanding of the distribution of these water mass tracers in the ocean. Here we present the first measurements of &amp;lt;0.45 μm-filtrate REE concentrations (i.e., the concentration of truly dissolved, nano-particulate and colloidal REEs passing through a 0.45 μm filter, hereafter referred to as dissolved) and εNd in rivers draining into the Canadian Arctic Archipelago (CAA). Results show a large variation in both REE concentrations (Nd=[8;37,260] pmol/kg) and εNd ([−32.1;−15.1]) in the thirteen rivers sampled. Dissolved REE concentrations increase with increasing fractions of metamorphic rocks and ice cover in the rivers&amp;rsquo; watersheds, while εNd and PAAS-normalized REE patterns are inherited from the watershed&amp;rsquo;s bedrock lithology. The four rivers draining watersheds composed of Precambrian metamorphic rocks exhibit the highest REE concentrations, the least radiogenic εNd, and shale-normalized patterns enriched in light REEs. The remaining nine rivers drain mainly or exclusively sedimentary bedrock and have lower REE concentrations, more radiogenic εNd and generally show heavy REE enrichment, with variable negative cerium (Ce) anomalies. The presence of ice sheets in the drainage area, and the ionic strength, pH, and dissolved organic carbon concentration of river water are the main factors determining riverine dissolved REE concentrations by controlling the formation and stabilization of colloids. We estimate a flow of dissolved Nd transported by Arctic rivers discharging into the CAA equivalent to the Nd flux of seawater entering the CAA. Depending on the percentage of Nd removal during mixing with seawater, the impact of river water on the εNd of seawater exiting the CAA could be modest (if 90% removal) or more significant (if ≪90% removal). This riverine contribution could potentially impart a climate-sensitive εNd signature to the seawater reaching Baffin Bay, with possible implications for the use of εNd in paleoceanographic reconstructions of water mass distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alterations in the sterol signature of detritivorous fish along pollution gradients in the Río de la Plata basin (Argentina): From plant to sewage-based diet
</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/er_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/er_2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;ER2020.png&#34; width=&#34;900px&#34; max-height= auto border=&#34;10&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: In order to assess the impact of sewage pollution on the diet of the strict detritivorous and migratory South American fish, Prochilodus lineatus, 16 sterol biomarkers were analyzed by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry from fish muscle (n: 144) collected along 1200 km in the Rio de la Plata basin. Sterol concentrations were fairly homogeneous (2.4 ± 1.3 mg g−1 dry weight), but their proportion in lipids was highly variable and inversely related to both body mass and lipid contents, reflecting the more conservative character of sterols compared to the rapid accumulation of fat as fish grows. As expected, the muscle sterol signature was widely dominated by cholesterol (92 ± 4.5% of total sterols), but it exhibited a remarkable diversity with variable proportions of fecal coprostanol (4.0 ± 4.4%) and plant sterols (3.1 ± 1.9%, e.g. sitosterol and campesterol). Muscle sterols exhibited contrasting geographical differences associated with dietary shifts from plant-derived detritus in the northern reaches of the basin (N: Paraná and Uruguay Rivers), to sewage dominated inputs at Buenos Aires (BA). Fish from BA are fattier (lipids: 35 ± 18 vs. 15 ± 9.0% at N), with higher total sterol contents (2.6 ± 1.3 vs. 1.9 ± 1.0 mg g−1), abundant coprostanol (5.3 ± 4.4 vs. 0.46 ± 1.1%) and lower plant sterols (2.6 ± 1.6 vs 4.6 ± 2.0%), reflecting a diet shifted to anthropogenic organic matter as opposed to vegetal detritus in the north. Accordingly, BA fish presented lower phyto/fecal sterol ratios (0.37 ± 0.21 vs. 0.91 ± 0.12 at N) and higher copro/epicoprostanol ratios (0.95 ± 0.082 vs 0.51 ± 0.25 at N), indicating fresh fecal inputs which provide a valuable supply of easily absorbed organic matter at this site. In addition, the sterol signature allowed to distinguish migratory fish from BA collected 900 km north (previously identified by their pollutant fingerprint and biochemical composition). In fact, coprostanol concentrations show a direct relationship with human populations along the basin, highlighting the usefulness of fecal sterol biomarkers as tracers of polluted fish stocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trace metal geochemistry of remote rivers in the Canadian Arctic Archipelago
</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/cg_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/cg_2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;CG2019.png&#34; width=&#34;900px&#34; max-height= auto border=&#34;10&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Trace metals are essential micronutrients for phytoplankton, as well as useful tracers of biogeochemical processes in aquatic systems. The largest Arctic rivers are known to play an important role in the cycling of trace metals in the Arctic Ocean; however, these systems account for little more than half of Arctic freshwater discharge, leaving a major gap in our understanding of the trace metal geochemistry from smaller river systems. This is especially problematic for rivers draining the Arctic coastal margins, as these continuous permafrost systems are anticipated to be particularly sensitive to climate change. This study presents the first observations of dissolved and particulate trace metal concentrations and lead isotopes in 14 rivers in the Canadian Arctic Archipelago (CAA). Dissolved concentrations of aluminum, iron, manganese, nickel, copper, zinc, cadmium, and lead display clear spatial variability in their distributions. Small rivers located in the central islands of the CAA have remarkably low concentrations of these trace metals, while the rivers draining the southern continental landmass have higher values. This geographic variability in dissolved metal concentrations reflects both differences in bedrock geology and the South-North environmental gradients in the Archipelago. We extrapolate these findings to estimate the dissolved trace metal concentrations for other rivers draining the CAA based on their geographic location. Elemental ratios measured in the suspended particulate matter in several rivers indicates a significant enrichment of nickel, copper, zinc, and lead over the crustal composition. In particular, lead isotope composition shows an extremely large range, varying from the highly radiogenic Tree River (206Pb/207Pb: 1.5121) in the south, to the relatively unradiogenic Glacier River (206Pb/207Pb: 1.0153) in the central CAA. Lack of correlation between the Pb isotopic composition and Pb enrichment, suggests Pb is derived from within the watershed. This work presents the first observations of dissolved and particulate trace metal concentrations in small coastal draining rivers from the CAA, an important first step in developing a baseline against which to evaluate future change in the high Arctic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early diagenetic alterations of sterol biomarkers during particle settling and burial in polluted and pristine areas of the Rio de la Plata Basin</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/og_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/og_2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;OG2018.png&#34; width=&#34;900&#34; height=&#34;900&#34; border=&#34;10&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Sources and diagenetic alterations of sterol markers were studied in settling material and sediments near the Buenos Aires main sewer (BA), and at a relatively non-polluted northern site at the Uruguay River (N). Vertical particle fluxes were 7-times higher at BA relative to N (34 ± 24 vs 4.6 ± 3.6 mg/cm2/day; mean ± standard deviation), increasing during rainy months. Total sterol contents were consistently higher at BA, both in settling material (7140 ± 7905 vs 41 ± 47 μg/g at N) and sediments (708 ± 454 vs 1.9 ± 0.18 μg/g). This difference was further amplified in the vertical flux of sterols (116 ± 168 vs 0.070 ± 0.13 mg/cm2/year). At BA, sterol composition of settling material and sediments was dominated by fecal sterols (75–77%), with extreme coprostanol concentrations (3.6 ± 4.8 vs 0.35 ± 0.28 mg/g at N) which are similar to sewage sludge. In contrast, at N the sterol profile was dominated by plant sterols (57–64%), mainly sitosterol, stigmasterol and campesterol. At BA the discharge of fresh sewage was confirmed by the high coprostanol/(coprostanol + epicoprostanol) ratio. At N, the overwhelming dominance of plant sterols over herbivore fecal sterols was reflected by the high sitosterol/(sitosterol + 24-ethylcoprostanol) ratio and the low coprostanol/(coprostanol + 24-ethylcoprostanol) ratio. The coprostanol/(coprostanol + epicoprostanol) and cholesterol/(cholesterol + cholestanol) ratios were lower in sediments than in settling material, reflecting the sterol degradation at the sediment surface. The accumulation efficiencies, calculated as the difference between trap fluxes and sediment inventories, were 2–7 times higher at BA reflecting strong vertical fluxes and enhanced preservation under anoxic conditions. During diagenetic processes, epicoprostanol (partially produced in situ), cholestanol and plant sterols were the best-preserved sterols, while cholesterol was the most labile during burial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fatty acid alterations in the detritivorous Prochilodus lineatus promoted by opportunistic feeding on sewage discharges in the Río de la Plata estuary</title>
      <link>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/jfb_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://Colombo-Manuel.github.io/publications/jfb_2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;JFB.png&#34; width=&#34;900&#34; height=&#34;900&#34; border=&#34;10&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Muscle fatty acid profiles and PCB contents of the detritivorous species Prochilodus lineatus and its diet (stomach contents, settling particles and sediments) were analysed from reference and polluted areas of the Paraná-Rio de la Plata basin, to evaluate the alterations produced by opportunistic feeding on sewage discharges. Overall muscle fatty acid composition was dominated by saturated and monounsaturated 16 and 18 carbon (18 C-FA) components with reduced long-chain polyunsaturated fatty acids (LC-PUFA). Compared to sediments, settling particles and stomach contents were enriched in lipids and had a similar fatty acid composition. Opportunistic feeding on sewage detritus at Buenos Aires resulted in enhanced PCB and triglyceride accumulation, with higher proportions of 18 C-FA and lower proportions of 16:1 and LC-PUFA compared to fish from northern pristine reaches of the basin. Mid-Paraná showed intermediate values reflecting mixing of the North stock with migrating Buenos Aires P. lineatus identified by their lipid and contaminant profile. According to multivariate analyses, this geographical variation of fatty acid composition was strongly influenced by PCB concentration. Prochilodus lineatus assimilates the energy subsidy of sewage inputs through enhanced lipogenesis with dominant 18 C-FA and significant amounts of valuable LC-PUFA. This lipid alteration facilitates the bioaccumulation of PCBs which in turn may reinforce the adipogenic effect of sewage feeding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;body {text-align: justify}&lt;/style&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
